"ApoE—The Single Most Important
Gene for Longevity"
Though the genetic
contribution to lifespan
may be relatively minor,
are there specific genes
that have been associated
with longevity?
The leading method
for complex genetic mapping
is called genome-wide
association analysis,
which is essentially
a massive game of Go Fish,
comparing a million or more
letters of DNA
between groups
of similar people,
looking for a match.
So for example,
if you stretch out the DNA
of hundreds of centenarians
and compare those sequences
to that of noncentenarians,
is there a DNA letter
at a certain position
that centenarians share
disproportionately?
The problem is
hundreds of centenarians
are all researchers are
typically able to find.
Extremely long-lived
individuals,
such as centenarians,
comprise only a tiny fraction
of the population,
on the order of
1 in 10,000 or so.
As you can imagine,
the more people you have in
a genome-wide association study,
the more likely
you'll be able to find
a needle in the DNA haystack.
With so few people
available to study
for extreme longevity research,
it becomes much more difficult
to identify trends.
Some researchers have tried
solving this problem
by lowering the age requirement
to 85.
Then you can enroll
thousands into your study,
but making it to 90
is not the same
as making it to 100.
In fact, statistically, it's
as hard to get from 90 to 100
as it is to get to 90
in the first place.
So, by using
younger age brackets,
we may miss out on discovering
some secret centenarian sauce.
That brings us to the largest
genome-wide association study
of lifespan to date,
based on data
from a million people.
How were researchers able
to include so many subjects?
By correlating
the genetic fingerprints
of half a million
middle-aged individuals
with the ages
of both of their parents,
they were able to find
a dozen DNA regions
linked to lifespan
that appeared to account for
up to five years' difference
between individuals.
Twelve DNA markers is actually
a surprisingly low number,
compared to height,
for example,
which is determined by more than
400 different DNA spots--
although, unlike lifespan,
height is highly heritable.
A review of all
of the genome-wide
association studies
for longevity put together
only found one gene confirmed
in multiple independent
meta-analyses:
the "Alzheimer's gene,"
APOE.
Beyond just determining
lower or higher dementia risk,
APOE is the single
most important gene
when it comes to longevity--
though again, that's not
necessarily saying much.
APOE codes for a protein
that is 299 amino acids long
called apolipoprotein E.
Some people have APOE genes
that code for the protein
with the amino acid cysteine
at positions 112 and 158,
known as the APOE2 variant,
while others have
an arginine in those spots--
the APOE4 variant
of the protein,
and APOE3 is the third major
type of variant,
which has one of each.
Having genes that code
for the APOE4 variant
increases your risk
of cognitive decline,
full-blown Alzheimer's disease,
and premature death.
If you have one copy
of the APOE4 gene
from your mother or father,
your odds of becoming
a centenarian
are cut roughly in half,
and if you have APOE4 genes
from both parents,
your centenarian odds drop
by more than 80 percent.
What does this protein do
to have such a powerful impact
on our health and longevity?
APOE is the primary cholesterol
carrier in the brain
and plays a major role
packaging and transporting
LDL cholesterol
throughout the body.
The LDL cholesterol level
in those with APOE4 genes
averages more than
40 points higher
than those with APOE2 genes,
gunking up the arteries that
feed both the heart and brain.
LDL cholesterol is a risk factor
not just for heart disease
but Alzheimer's disease
as well.
Switch people to a diet
lower in animal fat
and cholesterol, though,
and those LDL differences
can disappear,
nearly a 60-point drop in LDL.
The difference
in cholesterol level
caused by
the different APOE genes
can simply disappear
if you eat a diet low enough in
saturated fat and cholesterol.
So diet can trump genetics.
This may explain
the so-called Nigerian paradox.
If you inherit one APOE4 gene,
your risk of getting Alzheimer's
may triple,
and if you get APOE4 genes
from both parents--
which occurs in about one
in fifty people in the US--
you might end up
with nine times the risk.
The highest frequency
of the APOE4 variant
occurs in Nigerians,
but they also have
some of the lowest rates
of Alzheimer's disease.
How can that be?
The population with the highest
rate of the "Alzheimer's gene"
has one of the lowest rates
of Alzheimer's disease?
This contradiction
may be explained
by Nigerians' extremely low
blood-cholesterol levels,
thanks to a diet
low in animal fat,
and consisting mainly
of grains and vegetables.
Humans may have evolved
to maintain an LDL level
of about 25,
but the average
in the Western world
is approximately 120.
It's no wonder heart disease
is the leading cause of death
in high-income countries,
and Alzheimer's disease,
according to
the World Health Organization,
is killer #2.
Too often, doctors and patients
have a fatalistic approach
to chronic
degenerative diseases,
and Alzheimer's is no exception.
"It's all in your genes,"
they say,
"and what will happen
will happen."
But research shows that although
you might have been dealt
some poor genetic cards,
you may be able
to reshuffle the deck with diet.